<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book version="5.0" xml:id="spring-roo-developer-guide" xml:lang="es"
      xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
      xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title xml:lang="es">gvNIX - Documentación de desarrollo</title>

    <productname>gvNIX: Spring Roo based Java development framework.</productname>

    <releaseinfo>1.4.0-SNAPSHOT</releaseinfo>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <personname><link xlink:href="http://www.disid.com"
        xlink:show="new">DiSiD Technologies S.L.</link></personname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <legalnotice>
      <para xml:lang="es">Copyright 2010 - 2013 Consejería de Infraestructuras, Transporte
      y Medio Ambiende - Generalidad Valenciana</para>

      <para xml:lang="es">Esta obra está bajo la licencia Reconocimiento-Compartir bajo la
      misma licencia 3.0 España <link
      xlink:href="???">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/es/</link>
      de Creative Commons. Puede copiarla, distribuirla y comunicarla
      públicamente siempre que especifique sus autores y comparta cualquier
      obra derivada bajo la misma licencia. La licencia completa se puede
      consultar en <link
      xlink:href="???">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/es/</link></para>
    </legalnotice>
  </info>

  <toc/>

  <part>
    <title>TODO</title>

    <chapter>
      <title>TODO</title>

      <section>
        <title>Temas a tener en cuenta para documentar</title>

        <para>Recopilado de alguna tarea de documentación.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Remove all @Reference PathResolver declarations from classes
            and retrieve PathResolver from ProjectMetadata instead
            #4615</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Descripción de la tarea
            https://jira.springsource.org/browse/ROO-2066 sobre la
            conveniencia de uso de las distintas clases habituales en un
            add-on de Roo:</para>

            <para>Currently ClasspathOperations is injected into DBRE and MVC
            services. Roo Operations classes should only be called by other
            Operations classes. This change will re-factor out all the methods
            from ClasspathOperations into the existing TypeLocationService and
            a new TypeManagementService. Also, entity-specific commands will
            be moved from ClasspathCommands to a new EntityCommands class (and
            corresponding EntityOperations interface and impl class) located
            in addon-entity. Methods remaining in ClasspathCommands will be
            specific to classes and interfaces only. ClasspathOperations and
            ClasspathOperations will be removed after the MVC dependencies are
            changed to use TypeLocationService and TypeManagementService.
            Below is the background from Ben Alex about this change. </para>

            <para>The general pattern is this:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Utils are statless public abstract classes with public
                static methods. They cannot be instantiated or injected with
                anything. It's OK to pass things into the methods if it helps,
                but it is fairly unusual to pass services or complex objects
                given utility methods are simple.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Commands contain shell annotations. Generally call
                Operations, but can call Services as well. Usually deal with
                formatting for user I/O. Also ensure all types are of the
                intended format for successful method invocation.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Operations are stateless types which respond to UI
                commands and offer their methods to other Operations types.
                The point was they were different from Commands because they
                didn't deal with all the user I/O (preparing method arguments
                etc) nor did they deal with complex lifecycles requiring state
                and listener models like most of the metadata infrastructure
                and services do. They just did something quite simple and
                returned, with no ongoing lifecycle obligations. They are
                allowed call services and other Operations objects. They
                aren't allowed call Commands.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Services can be called by anyone, including control
                flows unrelated to a UI command, such as control flows
                instigated due to a MetadataProvider or event. Services should
                never call an Operations or Command object.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Listeners are really a special type of Service. Most of
                the time a so-called Service actually implements one of more
                Listeners.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>MetadataProviders and metadata infrastructure can call
                other metadata infrastructure and Services. They're really
                just a very special type of service (due to the ability to
                identify them and invoke and notify them from string-based
                MIDs). They follow the same rules as Services, namely they
                cannot call Operations or Commands.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>As time has gone on, more complex add-ons have needed to do
            more complex things and as such more and more logic has moved from
            Operations to Services to make them more sophisticated and
            generally available. This is what has happened in your case. It is
            starting to get to the point where I question the value of keeping
            the Operations concept at all. Sure, they're stateless and not
            listeners, but aside from that they seem of negligible distinction
            versus a service. Maybe we should just rename all Operations to
            Services for consistency? The critical thing is one cannot "call
            up" to Commands, as it's silly to re-convert missing arguments and
            figure out defaults etc like the Commands and Converter
            infrastructure does.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>"addon create advanced" y "addon create wrapper"</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Joey infrastructure
            https://jira.springsource.org/browse/ROO-1372 -
            http://projects.disid.com/issues/3814</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Allow third party addons to "override" methods generated by
            base addons (ie express an ordering preference) -
            https://jira.springsource.org/browse/ROO-795</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Ambigious command in Shell -
            https://jira.springsource.org/browse/ROO-726</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Configuración de las convenciones Java, save actions, etc.
            para el desarrollo del framework.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </chapter>
  </part>

  <part xml:id="introduccion-part">
    <title xml:lang="es">Introducción al desarrollo de gvNIX</title>

    <partintro>
      <para xml:lang="es">Esta parte de la documentación de introducción a la
      arquitectura interna y información básica para el desarrollo de
      gvNIX.</para>

      <para xml:lang="es">Antes de empezar a trabajar en gvNIX es conveniente
      leer la siguiente documentación:<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Operations, Commands, Utils et all:
            https://jira.springsource.org/browse/ROO-2066</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Joey infraestructure:
            https://jira.springsource.org/browse/ROO-1372</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </partintro>

    <xi:include href="arquitectura-interna.xml"/>

    <xi:include href="puntos-entrada.xml"/>

    <xi:include href="metadatos.xml"/>
  </part>

  <part xml:id="desarrollo-part">
    <title xml:lang="es">Desarrollo de gvNIX</title>

    <partintro>
      <para xml:lang="es">Esta parte de la documentación contiene la
      información de desarrollo de gvNIX</para>
    </partintro>

    <xi:include href="convenciones.xml"/>
    
    <xi:include href="calidad-codigo.xml"/>

    <xi:include href="repositorio.xml"/>

    <xi:include href="metodologia.xml"/>

    <xi:include href="creacion-addon.xml"/>

    <xi:include href="comandos.xml"/>

    <xi:include href="escucha-eventos.xml"/>

    <xi:include href="cambios-ficheros.xml"/>

    <xi:include href="crear-itd.xml"/>

    <xi:include href="compilacion.xml"/>

    <xi:include href="validacion.xml"/>

    <xi:include href="distribucion.xml"/>
  </part>

  <part>
    <title>OSGi</title>

    <partintro>
      <para xml:lang="es">Introducción a OSGi, add-ons como componentes
      OSGi.</para>
    </partintro>

    <xi:include href="osgi-intro.xml"/>

    <xi:include href="osgi-api.xml"/>
  </part>

  <part xml:id="recursos-part">
    <title xml:lang="es">Recursos</title>

    <partintro>
      <para xml:lang="es">En esta parte podrá encontrar recursos útiles para
      el desarrollo de gvNIX</para>
    </partintro>

    <xi:include href="recetas.xml"/>
  </part>
</book>
